Finding Aid for Women’s League (University of Michigan) records, 1890-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women’s League (University of Michigan) records 1890-2011
University of Michigan. Women's League.
87358 Bimu F17 2
The records of the Women's League of the University of Michigan contain the League's constitution and articles of incorporation, reports, correspondence, minutes of the League and of women students' governing bodies, scrapbooks, presidents reports, and photographs; letters from Ella Wheeler Wilcox and William Dean Howells; also papers of Edith M. Wheeler and Sarah Mills Gayley Browne.
39.25 linear feet
4 oversize volumes
2 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received in several accessions from the Women’s League (Donor No. 1908 ) beginning in 1943 and continuing through 1968. Additional material was received in 1970 through the University of Michigan Alumni Association (Donor No. 1617 ). Additional records were received from the Michigan League (Donor No. 8562 ) in 1997 and May 2009.
The record group is open for research.
From the time that women were admitted to the University of Michigan in 1870 (some four decades after the university's founding) until 1896, when the first dean of women was appointed, there was no organized supervision of women students on campus. The university provided no housing for students; female students, like their male counterparts, were left to find their own lodgings in town, usually in mixed rooming houses. Few of these rooming houses had sitting rooms for receiving callers.
Given the small number of women students on campus in proportion to the men, and lacking dormitories or places on campus where they might meet, women students at times felt isolated. As one early student related: "Of social life we had none, and in sheer despair of ever becoming acquainted with one another we founded a society mildly literary and aggressively friendly." The Women's League, of which this student spoke, was organized in 1890 by women students and wives of faculty members.
The Women's League had both social and governing functions. The league sponsored meetings, dances, and lectures; welcomed new students and helped them find housing; and, after the turn of the century, regulated rooming houses. Events such as the Freshman Spread, the Women's Banquet, and the Junior Girls' Play, an annual musical comedy first produced in 1904, were also held under the aegis of the Women's League. Through the efforts of league members, separate rooming houses for women, known as League Houses, were established in the early twentieth century. The league also played a prominent role in the movement for dormitories on campus.
The league was governed by a student executive committee and an advisory committee made up of women known as associate members. The advisory and executive committees held regular business meetings together and separately as necessary. Beginning with the academic year 1919-20, all women students were assessed an annual fee of one dollar, which went to the Women's League, and all women students automatically became members of the Women's League upon admission to the university.
In June 1891 the Detroit branch of the Collegiate Alumnae initiated a campaign to raise funds for a women's building on the University of Michigan campus adjacent to the new men's gymnasium then under construction. Over the next several years the league raised funds for this proposed women's building, which opened in 1896 as an annex to Waterman Gymnasium. The women's gymnasium, named for the principal donor, Regent Levi Barbour, was opened the following year, and in 1900 parlors were completed. Housing the offices of the dean of women, Barbour Gymnasium became the focus of women's social activities on campus for the next three decades, until the ever-increasing number of women students outgrew the building.
In 1921, shortly after the completion of the Michigan Union building, a million-dollar campaign was launched by the Alumnae Council of the Alumni Association to raise funds for a women's building on campus. The Regents agreed to provide the land if the alumnae could raise $500,000 or more to construct and endow the building. The state legislature appropriated $350,000 in 1927 for the purchase of a site. The building was designed by the firm of Irving K. Pond and Allen Pond, the same architecture firm that designed the Michigan Union. The Michigan League building opened on May 4, 1929, although formal dedication ceremonies were not held until June 14, 1929 in the Lydia Mendelssohn Theater.
The Michigan League building was initially governed by the Alumnae Council, in cooperation with the Board of Regents. Due to difficulties in meeting operating expenses, the Alumnae Council gave the building to the university in 1930 and a governing board composed of alumnae, faculty, and students was created. Beginning in 1933, a portion of the fees paid by women students was allocated to the maintenance of the building; thereafter all women students were members of the Michigan League.
To eliminate confusion between the Women's League as an organization and the Michigan League building, the administration of the building and the student organization were combined under the title Michigan League in 1934-35; the Women's League became the Undergraduate Division. Under this organization, students were given a greater share in the responsibilities of the board of governors, with the league president serving as chairman. A board of representatives composed of the Assembly and Panhellenic Association drafted regulations and decided questions of student government, while the Judiciary Council, elected by the women's student body, enforced these rules. In 1950 the Undergraduate Division once again assumed its original title, the Women's League, while the Michigan League persisted as the name of the building.
In the course of the 1960s the governance and activities of men and women students were gradually united and the need for a separate women's governing body diminished. The Women's League was gradually subsumed under general student governance. Women were admitted to the Student Government Council and in 1961 the offices of the dean of men and the dean of women were replaced by the Office of Student Affairs. In June 1963 the Board of Regents approved the creation of the Student Activities Center, which merged the student activities of the Michigan League and the Michigan Union. The league and union buildings continued to operate under distinct management.
The records of the Women's League date from 1890 to 1965 and measure 33 linear feet. The records are divided into eight series: Women's League (records of the organization), Michigan League (records of the building), Administrative, Students, Union-League Merger, Photographs, and Scrapbooks and Architectural records. The records span the life of the organization and are especially strong for the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, however many of the subseries include records for only a year or two. The bulk of the records are President's Reports, which consist of two to five large bound volumes for each academic year. The subseries in the last five series are arranged alphabetically by type of material, and many are continuations of subseries from the first two series which were from an earlier accession.
Subjects:
Barbour Gymnasium (University of Michigan); Michigan League.; University of Michigan. Alumnae Council.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1931-1940.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1951-1960.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan. Women's League.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Scrapbooks.; Browne, Sarah Mills Gayley.; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920.; Wheeler, Edith M.; Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919.
- Women's League 1890-1964
  The Women's League records are arranged in alphabetical order by type of material, with the exception of Histories, which have been placed at the beginning of the first box. The largest portion of this series consists of President's Reports dating from 1918/19 to 1962/63 (bulk 1933/34-1962/63). In addition to the reports by the presidents of the Women's League, these massive volumes contain minutes, reports, and financial records of the various governing bodies such as the Women's Senate, the Judiciary Council, and Panhellenic and Assembly Associations and of such activities as Senior Night, the Junior Girls' Play, Soph Show, and Frosh Weekend. In addition, the volumes contain programs, newsletters, and other material documenting the league's activities.
  Also included in the Women's League series are minutes of the league and its board of directors, legal documents, financial records documenting fundraising for the Women's Building (Barbour Gymnasium) and women's athletic fields, programs and publicity relating to the Junior Girls' Play and other social activities, scrapbooks, and a small number of photographs. The photographs consist primarily of portraits and group shots of officers and members of the Women's League and Mortarboard. Also included are photographs of Field Day, 1912; the fancy dress party in 1914; and the cast of the 1914 production of "Jeanne d'arc." Of special note is the correspondence, which dates from the earliest years of the organization's existence and includes autobiographical sketches written by alumnae in 1896 and letters by such prominent literary figures as Ella Wheeler Wilcox and W.D. Howells expressing their views on athletic education for women. (The latter were written in response to an appeal for support of the league's campaign for a women's gymnasium and were published in the April 1896 issue of The Invader.)
  - Histories
    - 1896, 1898-1899 (Box 1)
    - 1907-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1924, 1928, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Social Committee Reports 1925-1931 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Committee Reports 1918/19 (Box 1)
  - Constitution
    - 1890-1893 (includes membership list) (Box 1)
    - 1890-1896 (includes membership lists and history) (Box 1)
    - 1926, 1937-1938, 1947, undated (Box 1)
    - 1955-1964, undated (Box 1)
      (includes lists and history)
  - Correspondence
    - 1893 (Box 1)
    - 1895 (Box 1)
    - 1896
      - General (Box 1)
      - Re: Athletic Education for Women (Box 1)
      - Autobiographical Sketches by Alumnae (Box 1)
    - 1897-1898 (Box 1)
    - 1905-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1964 (includes reports re: Union-League merger) (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Deeds 1908-1911 (Box 1)
  - Financial
    - Account Book
      - 1890/91-1896/97 (Box 1)
      - 1900/01-1907/08 (Box 1)
      - 1908/09-1913/14 (Box 1)
      - 1914/15-1916/17 (Box 1)
    - League House Fund: Treasurer's Book 1909/10 (Box 1)
    - League Undergraduate Fund 1962, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Palmer Field Club House Fund 1922 (Box 1)
    - Recreation Field Fund
      - Pledges 1908-1909 (Box 1)
      - Treasurer's Book 1908/09-1909/10 (Box 1)
    - Residence Hall Fund
      - Petition 1909/10 (Box 1)
      - Subscriptions 1911/12 (Box 1)
      - Treasurer's Book 1909/10-1910/11 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Report 1914-1915 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1908-1916 (Box 1)
  - Governance
    - Assembly Association
      - Constitution (Box 1)
      - Dormitory and League House Presidents' Council: Minutes 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - Dormitory House Presidents' Council: Minutes 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Handbook (for officers and committees) 1959/60 (Box 1)
    - Honor Council
      - Constitution 1923-1925 (Box 1)
      - Minutes 1923-1925 (Box 1)
    - House Rules 1925-1927, undated (Box 1)
    - Judiciary Council
      - General 1916-1929, undated (Box 1)
      - History 1956 (Box 1)
    - Officers 1920/21, 1932/33-1934/35, undated (Box 1)
    - Organization Charts undated (Box 1)
    - Point [Merit] System 1925, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Report on Self Government 1927, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Guest Book (Box 2)
    (gift of Eliza Mosher)
  - Membership Lists
    - Potential Associate Members circa 1890s (Box 2)
    - 1908/09 (Box 2)
  - Minutes
    - Women's League
      - 1890/91-1897/98 (Box 2)
      - 1898/99 (Box 2)
      - 1899/1900-1903/04, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1905/06-1910/11 (Box 2)
      - 1912/13-1913/14 (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors
      - 1914/15-1917/18 (Box 2)
      - 1918/19-1929/30 (Box 2)
      - 1930/31-1931/32 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Board of Representatives
      - 1919-1931 (Box 2)
      - 1950 (Box 2)
  - Mortarboard
    - Reports 1937/38-1938/39 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook 1937/38-1941/42 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - General (Box 2)
    - Re: Union-League Merger,1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - 1905/06-1918, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1911/12-1937/38, 1 folders (Box 2)
  - President's Report
    - 1918/19, 1925/26-1927/28, 1931/32, 1933/34, 1 folders (Box 2)
    - 1934/35, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1935/36, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1936/37
      - Volume 1 (Box 3)
      - Volume 2 (Box 4)
    - 1937/38, 2 volumes (Box 4)
    - 1938/39, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - 1939/40, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - 1940/41, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - 1941/42, 1 volumes (Box 6)
    - 1942/43, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1944/45, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1945/46, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1946/47, 2 volumes
      - Volume 1 (Box 8)
      - Volume 2 (Box 9)
    - 1947/48, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - 1948/49, 3 volumes (Box 10)
    - 1949/50, 5 volumes (Box 11)
    - 1950/51, 4 volumes (Box 12)
      - Volumes 1-3 (Box 12)
      - Volume 4 (Box 13)
    - 1951/52, 4 volumes
      - Volumes 1-2 (Box 13)
      - Volumes 3-4 (Box 14)
    - 1952/53, 4 volumes
      - Volume 1 (Box 14)
      - Volumes 2-4 (Box 15)
    - 1953/54, 4 volumes
      - Volumes 1-3 (Box 16)
      - Volume 4 (Box 17)
    - 1954/55, 4 volumes
      - Volumes 1-2 (Box 17)
      - Volumes 3-4 (Box 18)
    - 1955/56, 4 volumes
      - Volume 1 (Box 18)
      - Volumes 2-4 (Box 19)
      - Volume 5 (Box 20)
    - 1956/57, 7 volumes
      - Volumes 1-3 (Box 20)
      - Volumes 4-6 (Box 21)
    - 1956/57 (Box 22)
      - Volume 7 (Box 22)
    - 1957/58, 6 volumes
      - Volumes 1-2 (Box 22)
      - Volumes 3-5 (Box 23)
      - Volume 6 (Box 24)
    - 1958/59, 7 volumes
      - Volumes 1-2 (Box 24)
      - Volumes 3-6 (Box 25)
      - Volume 7 (Box 26)
    - 1959/60, 6 volumes
      - Volumes 1-3 (Box 26)
      - Volumes 4-6 (Box 27)
    - 1960/61, 3 volumes
      - Volume 1 (Box 27)
      - Volumes 2-3 (Box 28)
    - 1961/62, 3 volumes
      - Volume 1 (Box 28)
      - Volumes 2-3 (Box 29)
    - 1962/63, 3 volumes (Box 29)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1911/12-1915/16, 1 folders (Box 30)
    - 1925-1937, 14 volumes (Box 30)
  - Social Activities
    - Dance Club Program 1934 (Box 31)
    - Freshman Spread: Account Book 1920/21-1921/22 (Box 31)
    - Junior Girls' Play
      - Account Book 1918/19-1921/22 (Box 31)
      - Programs 1931, 1933 (Box 31)
      - Scrapbook 1949-1950 (Box 34)
      - Scripts, 2 folders (Box 31)
      - Sheet Music "8 Till 8," 1927 (Box 31)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
    - Michigan Women's Luncheon: Reports 1917-1922, 1924 (Box 31)
    - Undergraduate Campaign Fund: Minutes and Reports 1923-1928 (Box 31)
  - Student Records: Record of Credit for Barbour Gymnasium Classes 1909/10-1913/14 (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Alumnae Council: Reports and Correspondence circa 1931, 1964-1965, undated (Box 31)
    - Biographical Information re Distinguished Alumnae (Box 31)
    - Chapel Survey for Michigan League 1962 (Box 31)
    - Housing Department Training Manual undated (ca. 1990) (Box 31)
    - "Memorial to Mrs. Gayley Browne," 1895 (Box 31)
    - Printed material 1890s, 1928 (Box 31)
    - Sororities at Michigan 1920 (Box 31)
    - Spanish-American War: Letter of thanks to Women's League from Company A, Thirty-first Regiment, Michigan Volunteer Infantry June 14, 1898 (Box 31)
    - University of Michigan Women's Contributions to the War Effort (WW II) 1942-1943 (Box 31)
- Michigan League 1920-2007
  The Michigan League series is also arranged alphabetically by type of material, with histories placed at the beginning. The material in this series relates primarily to the fundraising campaign for the Michigan League building and to the operations of the building. Included are correspondence, minutes of the board of governors and executive committee, operating statements, legal and financial records of the building campaign, scrapbooks of the League Library, and a memoir written by Edith Wheeler, who served as manager of the Michigan League from 1947 to 1956. The correspondence relates for the most part to the search for a business manager for the league in the year prior to its opening; the large number of highly qualified female applicants from across the country indicates the widespread interest in the idea of a women's center in a university setting.
  - Histories
    - Edith M. Wheeler Memoir: "The Michigan League from January 1947-July 1956" (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous Histories (Box 31)
  - Board of Governors
    - Archivist and Record Retention Policy 1997-2006 (Box 31)
    - Building Use Criteria 2006-2007 (Box 31)
    - Governor's Manual 1996 (Box 31)
    - Membership Lists and Miscellaneous, 1934-2007 (scattered) (Box 31)
    - Reports to the Board 1988-1993 (Box 31)
    - Rules and Regulations 1941, 1947, undated (Box 31)
    - Training Manual 1998 (Box 31)
  - Building Campaign
    - General (Box 31)
    - Contracts (Box 31)
    - Correspondence 1920-1924 (Box 31)
    - Pledge Cards
      - circa 1920-1934 (Box 33)
        (Cards with names of individuals and organizations making donations to the League, filed alphabetically. Some cards are cross-referenced with the ledgers by pledge number.)
    - Ledgers (Box 33)
    - Pledges
      - 1921-1924, 1 volumes (Box 33)
      - 1924-1926, 1 volumes (Box 33)
      - Receipts 1921-1925, 1 volumes (Box 33)
    - Progress Report on Building and Endowment Fund June 1924 (Box 31)
    - University of Michigan League Building Association
      - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws 1924-1927, 1934 (Box 31)
      - Minutes 1924 (Box 31)
  - Building Operations
    - Analysis of Operations 1946 (Box 31)
    - Plans for Operating Building 1928 (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
  - Committees
    - Committee on Opening Day of the League Building: Minutes May 4, 1929 (Box 31)
    - Theatre Committee: Report 1929 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence
    - General 1928-1929 (Box 31)
    - Business Manager Search 1928-1929, 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Executive Committee
    - Minutes 1929 (Box 31)
  - League Library Scrapbooks
    - 1929-1952 (Box 31)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 31)
  - Operating Statements
    - 1934-1962, 10 volumes (Box 32)
  - Guest Book, 1 volumes (Box 34)
    (given by Battle Creek Group of Michigan Alumnae, 1931)
- Administrative 1928-2009
  The Administrative series documents the governance and functioning of the Michigan League. The Board of Governors subseries comprises a significant minority of the Administrative records and may be seen as an extension of the earlier Michigan League's Board of Governors subseries (Box 31).
  The Building subseries differs from the earlier Building Operations subseries (Box 31) in its documentation of a later period (primarily the 1960s) and in its focus on students' access to the facilities. In the Financial subseries, the Operating Statements and League Undergraduate Fund complement pre-existing series (Box 32 and Box 1 respectively).
  - Board of Governors
    - Minutes Index 1933-1996 (Box 35)
    - Minutes, 1928-1965, 14 folders (Box 35)
    - Minutes 1966-1997, 31 folders (Box 36)
    - Minutes 1998-2011, 11 folders (Box 37)
    - Bylaws 1956-1988, 2006, 3 folders (Box 37)
    - Executive Committee Minutes 1951-1968 (Box 37)
    - Executive Committee Minutes and Executive Review Committee Minutes 1975-1991 (Box 37)
    - Executive Session Minutes 1956-1965 (Box 37)
    - House Committee Minutes 1958-1985, 2 folders (Box 37)
    - League Program and Development Committee 1968 (Box 37)
    - Manual for Board Members 1967, 1990 (Box 37)
    - Rosters 1953-1979, 1986-1987 (Box 37)
    - Student Officer on Board of Governors 1966-1968 (Box 37)
  - Building
    - Lunch Buffet Survey 1991-1993 (Box 37)
    - Remodeling 1964-1967, 1985, 1998-1999 (Box 37)
    - Space Allocation
      - Center for Continuing Education of Women 1959-1967 (Box 37)
      - General (Box 37)
      - House Rules (Box 37)
      - Report of the Committee on Space Allocation 1970 (Box 37)
        (also see Students, Student Organizations Use of League)
  - Financial
    - Account Books 1934-1957, 5 volumes (Box 38)
    - Building and Endowment Fund 1935-1936 (Box 38)
    - League Budget 1942-1945 (Box 38)
    - Report of Audit 1943 (Box 38)
    - Financial Reports 1978-1986 (Box 39)
    - Financial Reports 1987-1993, 1996 (Box 39)
    - League Undergraduate Fund 1959-1964 (Box 39)
    - Operating Statements 1965-1969, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Student Fees 1957-1981 (Box 39)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 39)
- Students 1956-1984
  The Students series documents student life's organizational dimensions. It includes the minutes of the Women's League Council and of the broader Student Government Council.
  - Office of Student Affairs (Box 39)
    - General (Box 39)
    - Clippings (Box 39)
  - Student Awards 1965-1984 (Box 39)
    (includes photograph)
  - Student Government Council 1968-1973 (Box 39)
    (includes minutes)
  - Student Organizations Use of League (Box 39)
  - Women's League Council Minutes 1956-1962, 5 folders (Box 39)
- Union-League Merger 1960-1973
  The Union-League Merger series expands on folders scattered in the earlier series. The General file joins with the Women's League Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 1) to document the merger's planning stages and expected relationship to established organizations. The Newspaper Clippings file adds to its counterpart in the Michigan League's subseries (Box 2). The University Activities Center (UAC) merged the student activities of the Michigan League and Michigan Union. Included in this subseries are the minutes of the Joint Council Committee, which was established in March 1965 to select officers and determine policies and procedures for the UAC. The series also documents UAC's changing structure and activities.
  - General (Box 39)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1963-1965 (Box 39)
  - Union-League Study Committee (Box 39)
  - University Activities Center (UAC)
    - Activities (Box 39)
    - Functioning and Reorganization, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Installation Services for New Officers 1960-1973 (Box 39)
    - Joint Council Committee Minutes and Reports to Board of Governors 1964-1973, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Senior Officers Reports 1965-1973 (Box 39)
- Photographs 1907-1949
  The Photographs series include portraits of the League presidents. The earliest date from 1890 and are in the oversize material. There are additional formal photographs from this period in the Women's League Photographs, 1911/12-1937/38 folder (Box 2). Also included in the Photographs series are posed and unposed photos from the Junior Girls' Play. These contribute to the pre-existing subseries Junior Girls' Play (Box 31), which documents the productions' planning and execution.
  - Junior Girls' Play 1933-1949 (Box 40)